Hello. We're going to start with some background
【未完成版本】大家好 我们将从平面微分几何领域的
in the area of planar differential geometry, the area of differential
一些背景知识讲起 关于平面微分几何领域和
geometry and the understanding of curves on the plain. Before I do that, I want to
平面上曲线的理解 在开始之前
provide some credit. I work a lot in the area of partial
我想先说明一下 我在数字图像处理的
differential equations in image processing, and some time ago I wrote a
偏微分方程领域做过很多研究 在不久前还写过一本相关的书
book.. My good colleague and friend Ron Kimmel
我的好友兼同事 罗恩 基梅尔 (Ron Kimmel)
also wrote a book in the area and we used to give a lot of talks independently.
在该领域也有一本著作 我们都曾独立做过很多讲座
I gave full semester classes, he gives full semester classes and sometimes we
我曾开过整个学期的课程 他也一样
give together tutorials on this subject. A lot of the slides I am using during
在这一课题上 我们有时会进行合作教学 在这周我要使用的
this week come from those tutorials and I want to thank Professor Kimmel for
很多幻灯片也是来自于那些合作教学的成果 在此我想感谢基梅尔教授
letting me share some of his slides and combining them with mine so that I can
允许我分享他的幻灯片 并且将之与我自己的相结合
provide the topic of partial differential equations in this week.
来进行这周的偏微分方程主题的讲解
Thank you Professor Kimmel for that. now, let's talk about curves, so we can
谢谢你 基梅尔教授 现在 我们来谈谈曲线
describe what do I mean by differential geometry of curves.
那样我们就能描述 我所说的曲线微分几何
So what's a curve on the plane? A curve on the plane will define a
那什么是平面上的曲线？ 对于平面上的曲线
coordinate system, and this is for convenience.
我们可以定义一个坐标系统
We have the X axis and the Y axis and then we define a curve parameterized by
方便起见 我们使用x轴和y轴 然后定义一个参数为P的曲线
P, we called P the parameter. P runs between zero and one, and for every value
我们称P为参数 其值介于0到1之间 而P的每一个值
of P, we get a coordinate in this axis, and a coordinate in this axis, and that's
都对应这个轴上的一个坐标 和这个轴上的一个坐标
a coordinate of one point on the curve. So, basically, for example, for P equals
这就是曲线上一点的坐标 举个例子 如果p=0.1
0.1, we get this point. Then for a different p like 0.7, we get
我们就得到这点 如果p=0.7 那我们得到另一点 以此类推
another point, and so on. So I'm sure you get the idea.
我想大家应该能明白这个意思
Basically a different values of p within zero and one give us different points on
P取0到1之间的不同值 就给出了曲线上不同的点
the curve. Now, if a curve is closed like here, what
如果一条曲线像这样闭合
we have is that c at zero. Is equal to C and one.
那么 我们就能得到 C(0)=C(1) 这个式子
So it starts and ends basically on the same point, and that's a closed curve.
这表示曲线的开始和结尾在相同的点上 也就是一条闭合曲线
Now you're very familiar with this concept.
现在大家应该对这一概念很熟悉了
If maybe you're not so familiar with curves but for sure you are familiar with
有可能大家还不是那么熟悉曲线 但大家一定对函数很熟悉
functions. So functions, you have a coordinate
那用函数来说 这是一个坐标系
system, X and Y as here, and you have a function, that for every value of X
X Y 轴在这里 然后有一个函数 对于每一个X值
there's one unique value of Y. That doesn't happen in normal curves.
有且只有一个对应的Y值 但对于常规的曲线而言 并不是这样的
In that case your curve is parmitrized by this coordinate itself so we get c of x
如果像函数那样 曲线通过坐标本身参数化 那我们就得到了c(x)
equal. The first coordinate is X by itself.
它的第一个坐标是X本身
That's the first coordinate, and the second is some function of it.
这是第一个坐标 而第二个坐标则是X的函数 f(x)
So these are just functions that you are very familiar with.
这些都是大家已经非常熟悉的函数表示形式
Again, the difference between a function and a general curve is that for each one
函数和一般曲线之间的差别就在于 对于每一个X轴坐标
of these coordinates, each one of the X's, there's only one Y, and that's why
只有一个Y坐标相对应 这就是为什么称之为函数
it's called a function. There's a, basically a unique value.
因为Y轴上只有唯一的一个值
So it's a particular case of a curve. We could think about curves also as a
这是曲线的一种特殊情况 我们可以认为曲线也是
generalization of functions on the plane. Now, once we understand the curve, which
函数在平面上的一般化形式 一旦我们理解了
is parameterized by this P, and we're going to discuss a lot about P in the
用参数P来表示的曲线 那我们在接下来的时间里
next few minutes. There's a couple of very important
就将深入讨论关于参数P的内容 关于平面上的曲线
concepts of curves on the plane, and two of them are the tangent and the normal.
有一些及其重要的概念 其中两个分别是 切线和法线
And also what we call the curvature, which we're going to explain in a second.
以及我们所说的曲率 一会儿我们将详细解释
Let's start from the tangent. Basically, we have a curve, and we can
让我们先来看切线 如果我们有一条曲线
take the derivative of this curve. So this is where differential equations,
那就能求这条曲线的导数 这就是微分方程
differential geometry starts to appear. C_PP stands for the derivative of C taken
微分几何学将出现的原因 Cp代表C关于p的导数
by p. So its basically CP.
写作Cp
It's just a simplifying notation of the derivative of C with respect to P, which
这简化了C关于p的导数的表示形式
is of course a vector, is the derivative of x with respect to p.
当然 这是一个矢量 等于x关于p的导数
C is a function of p, so I'm allowed to take the derivative of that,
C是p的函数 所以我可以这样取导数
Y as a function of P. so this is what we have here and we
y也是p的函数 这样就得到了这个
normalize by its length, we want to get that unit length and that's actually
我们取这一矢量的模 从而得到了单位长度的矢量
very, very important. As we are going to see, there is a
这一点至关重要 我们将会看到
particular parametrization called S that provides us a tangent that has unit
有一个特殊的参数S 规定了一个单位长度的切线
length. And we're going to use that a lot.
我们将会频繁地用到这个
And we're going to see how we go from P to S.
我们将会看到怎样从P得到S
But the basic idea is that we take a derivative of this curve.
但是基本思想是 我们对这一曲线求导
And you learn in your basic calculus class that the derivative of a function
而大家在基础微积分课堂上学过 对一个函数求导
gives you a vector which is perpendicular, but which is sorry, it's
得到一个向量 是垂直的 对不起 确切说是
tangent. To that function.
是与那一函数相切的
In a second we are going to talk about perpendicular.
一会儿我们会说到垂线
So once again, the derivative of a function gives you a vector which is
所以再强调一下 对函数求导得到一个向量
tangent to that function. So the derivative.
这一向量与原函数相切 所以说
Of this curve are vectors, which are tangent.
这条曲线的导数是与其相切的矢量
And they don't have to have unit length, so we normalize them, and there is one
而且并不需要有单位长度 因此我们对它们进行归一化
particular parmituzation we are going to write s that will give us a unit length.
这是一个特别的参数化 我们用s表示 它给出了一个单位长度的矢量
And again we are going to see how we go from one to the other.
我们将再次看到怎样从一个值 得到另一个值
Now what we are going to, now that we have the tangent, and in particular,
现在我们来看 我们已经得到了切线 而且特别地
bear with me for a second. We have the curve parameterized in such a
请容忍我一下 我们有了参数化的曲线
way that the tangent, meaning the derivative, is always unit length.
通过这样 使得切线 也就是导数 永远是单位长度
What do I mean by unit length? That the, basically the magnitude of the
单位长度指的是什么呢？ 就是指
derivative vector is equal to one. Okay?
导数向量的模等于1 明白了吗？
Unit length. Let's assume that I can basically write a
这就是单位长度 假设我能写出一个曲线的表达式
curve. Instead of a function of P, a function of
它不是一个关于p的函数
a different parameter S that gives me unit length.
而是一个关于另一个参数s的函数 这个参数给出了单位长度
Now length means, and I'm going to write this down and
长度的意思是 我要先把这个写出来
explain again, this means that the inner product of the vector with itself is
然后再解释 这个意思是 一个向量与它自己的内积等于1
equal one. If you don't remember what's the inner
如果大家不记得什么是 两个向量的内积
product between two vectors, is basically you multiply the first coordinate of
基本上就是 将向量1的第一个坐标
vector one by the first coordinate of vector two, and to that you sum the
与向量2的第一个坐标相乘 然后加上
product of the second coordinate of each vector.
两个向量第二个坐标的积
So it's X of the first times X of the second, plus Y of the first, times Y of
也就是 向量1的x 乘上向量2的x 加上 向量1的y 乘上向量2的y
the second. So that means that we have unit length.
这样我们就有了单位长度
Let's take a derivative of this. So I'm going to take a derivative according to s
我们来求这个式子的导数 在两边同时求关于s的导数
in both sides. So this is the derivative.
这是一个导数
A constant is always unit length, so this becomes zero.
这个常数永远是1 所以这个导数就等于0
The derivative of this is like any other product, it's the derivative of the first
这个的导数也像其他函数乘积的规则一样
times the second plus the derivative of the second times the first but because
是第一个的导数乘以第二个 再加上 第二个的导数乘以第一个
these are equal then this is two times the inner product of the first derivative
但是因为这些都是相等的 所以结果就是 一阶导数与二阶导数内积的两倍
with the second derivative. It's like any other product, okay?
就像其他的乘积的规则一样 明白了吗？
The two I can eliminate, and this means that the first derivative, according to
这个2可以消去 然后这个就表示 关于弧长的一阶导数
arc length, is perpendicular to the second derivative.
垂直于它的二阶导数
Once again, just to remind you, two, the inner product of two vectors is equal to
再次提醒大家一下 如果两个向量相互垂直
zero, if and only if one vector is perpendicular to the other.
那么它们的内积就等于0
So from here, we get that CS, the first derivative, is
所以从这里 我们得到Cs 也就是一阶导数
perpendicular to the second derivative. Now the magnitude of the first derivative
与二阶导数垂直 而一阶导数的模等于1
is one. The second derivative, we have it here,
而二阶导数 也就是这个
is perpendicular to the first one. All the time when we are taking
与一阶导数互相垂直 当我们求关于s的导数时
derivatives according to s, the first is unit vector, the second is perpendicular
一阶导数始终是单位向量 而二阶导数则与之垂直
to it. So this is the second derivative.
所以这就是二阶导数
Now it doesn't have to be a unit vector. Most of the time it won't.
它并不需要是一个单位向量 大多数情况下它也不是
And we call the magnitude of that second derivative we call the curvature.
我们将二阶导数的模称为曲率
This is the curvature. Okay, this is one definition of the
这就是曲率 那么 这就是曲率的一个定义
curvature. It basically tells us how much the
它可以告诉我们切向方向改变了多少
tangent is changing and it's very intuitive.
而且是非常直观的
If it changes a lot, it means that the curve is curving along there and has very
如果切向方向改变很大 就意味着曲线在那里弯曲得很厉害
high curvature. It it's not curving a lot, for example a
并且有着很高的曲率 如果曲线并没有太大弯曲 比如
straight line has zero curvature, so what's a tangent of a straight line?
一条直线 那么它的曲率就等于0 那么直线的切线是怎样的呢？
At every point it just changed colors. At every point the tangent is in the same
在每一点上 我来换一种颜色 在每一点上 切线沿着同一方向
direction. It's in the direction of the line.
也就是在这条线的方向
So the change of tangent, tangent is the first derivative, second derivative is
至于切线的改变 切线是一阶导数 那么它的变化量就成了二阶导数
the change. The change of the tangent is zero.
这个切线的变化量等于0
So a planner, basically a straight line has zero curvature.
所以 一条水平线 也就是一条直线 它的曲率等于0
What's a curvature of a circle? So we have to, basically again, draw the
那么一个圆的曲率是多少呢？ 为了知道这点 我们始终要
time change all the time. And then see how they're changing
首先画出它的切线 然后来看
infinitesimally when I move from one point to the other.
当我从一点移动到另一点时 它们怎样趋向于无穷小
Those are derivatives. Derivatives means when you're very, very
那些就是导数 它意味着当两个点非常接近时
close how is the tangent changing? First of all, it's constant because the
它们的切线是如何变化 首先 它是一个常数
circle is all the same. So it has to be constant curvature.
因为圆上的每个点都是一样的 所以曲率一定是个常数
And then it's not hard to prove that the curvature is one over the radius.
这样就不难证明 曲率等于半径的倒数
Okay, so the curvature is one over the radius of the circle.
明白了吧 曲率就是圆半径的倒数
The larger the circle, the more curvature it has, the, the, the, sorry, the larger
一个圆越大 曲率就越大 啊 对不起 说错了
the circle, the more radius it has, one over the radius, the smaller the
应该是圆越大 半径就越大 所以半径的倒数
curvature. You could think about a straight line as
也就是曲率就越小 大家可以把一条直线想象成
a circle with infinite radius, very, very large radius and then one over infinite
一个半径无穷大的圆 有着相当大的半径 而无穷大的倒数等于0
is zero, so basically has zero curvature. So there's a lot of new concepts in this
所以直线的曲率就等于0 我已经讲了大量新的概念
very colorful slide. Let's go over them again.
幻灯片上已经五颜六色了 让我们再来复习一下吧
We have the tangent which is as we know from basic functional analysis, basic
我们学习了切线 从函数分析
calculus, is basically the first derivative.
微积分的角度上来说 就是一阶导数
We want to normalize it, we want to have unit length and there is a
接着我们想对它进行归一化 想求出单位长度
parametrization, we're going to see how we get to it, that basically gives us
这是一个参数化过程 我们将会学习它是如何做转换的
that the first derivative is always unit length.
这让我们得到了 一阶导数永远是单位长度的
Always unit length we take a derivative of that concept and we get the second
总是单位长度的 针对这一概念 我们再求一次导 这样我们就
derivative which is always perpendicular to the first one only when we are talking
得到了二阶导数 在涉及到关于s的导数时
derivatives taking derivatives according to s.
二阶导数总是垂直于一阶导数的
And then that second derivative has a norm.
这样二阶导数就有了一个系数
Basic a demand to that vector and that's curvature.
也是该向量的模 这就是曲率
Curvature is the magnitude of the second derivative according to s.
曲率是曲线关于s的二阶导数的模
This is going to be called the arc length, as we are going to see in a
s被称作弧长 一会儿我们就会解释原因
second why. So we have s, the arc length.
这样我们就得到了弧长s
And we have. This is kappa, is the Greek letter kappa,
还得到了k 这是一个希腊字母
which is the curvature. Now we have s and the curvature and we
代表曲率 现在我们就有了s和曲率
talk about their relationship between the curvature and the radius of a circle.
而且我们还说到了 圆半径和曲率的关系
These are actually the only two objects with constant.
事实上 它们是仅有的两种曲线拥有恒定的曲率
El cleanant curvature straight line zero a circle one over the radius.
比如 直线的曲率是0 而圆的曲率则是半径的倒数
Now why are these guys s and curvature kappa.
那么为什么这两个量 s和曲率k 如此重要
So important. Very important, because they're going to
它们极其重要 因为它们
be preserved under transformations of the curve, under certain transformations.
在曲线的一些特定变换过程中 会被保留下来
What kind of transformations can we have in curves?
那对于曲线 我们能做些什么变换呢？
So, I have here a curve. Where's the curve?
【未完成版本】这里有一条曲线 曲线在哪里呢？
It's the boundary of my object. Now we are starting to understand why
就是这个对象的轮廓 现在我们知道
differential geometry is important, because curves are boundaries of objects
为何微分几何如此重要了 这是因为曲线是对象的轮廓
and objects are present in images. Now, I can transform these in a number of
而对象存在于图像之中 现在 我可以用多种方式对它们进行变换
ways, but always preserving it on the plane.
但总让它们保持在平面上
I generally transform is, I take my coordinates, which are a vector and I
一般这样变换 先取坐标 那是一个向量
multiply by a matrix and I translate and I get a new vector.
将它乘以一个矩阵 平移 得到一个新的向量
And that's what called an define transform, if I don't put any limitations
这就叫作仿射变换(Affine Transform) 如果在A这个矩阵中不加任何限制条件
in this matrix, so I take the curve and with an define transform, I transform it
对一条曲线作仿射变换 形成一条新的曲线
into a new curve. Now, I can also just rotate my shape.
也可以做一个旋转变换
Here it has the form, it has stretch in different dimensions in different
这里它变成了这样的形状 在不同维度不同方向伸展
directions. If I only want to translate and rotate,
如果我只想进行旋转和平移
so I rotate and translate or I translate and rotate, that imposes some limitations
旋转之后平移或者平移之后旋转 这就要对A加以限制
in A and it's not hard to show that in order to only allow rotations and
不难证明 如果只允许旋转和平移
translations, the two vectors of A, so A is a two by two matrix.
A得是一个2乘2矩阵
I have here a vector multiplied by a two by two matrix.
这里一个向量乘一个2乘2矩阵
Sorry, a vector that I get it by a matrix
抱歉 应该是一个矩阵乘以一个向量得到一个新向量
multiplying a vector. This has to have columns which are
这需要各列是正交的
orthogonal, meaning the inner product means zero we just saw that in the
意味着它们的内积要为0 正如之前幻灯片所看到的那样
previous slide. Inner product equals zero means
内积为0意味着正交
orthogonal, and they also have to be unit vectors.
且它们还需要是单位向量
So this is just not hard to prove, but important thing here is that you can do a
这不难证明 但重要的是
rotation and translation that's called a Euclidean motion, or can you, or you can
你可以旋转和平移 这叫做欧几里得运动 或者你可以
do a general transformation and that is called an affine motion and of course
做一般变形 称为仿射运动
these are too or these are also related by an affine motion.
这两个图同样可以通过仿射运动相关联
Now there's a particular think in a fine motions that if they the determinant of
仿射运动有个特殊性质 如果这个矩阵的行列式为1
this matrix is equal to one then basically those are called equal
那么就称它为等仿射运动
equi-affine motions, if the determinant is equal to one, what happens is that the
如果行列式等于1 那么这里的面积就不会改变
area doesn't change. So you can stretch differently, in
于是就可以在不同方向进行伸缩
different directions. You can rotate, you can translate but the
可以旋转 可以平移 但它的面积不变
area is preserved. Of course if you only allow Euclidean
当然也可以只做欧几里得运动
motions, rotations and translations, the area is preserved, but if you allow.
即旋转和平移  面积是不变的
A fine transformation stretches there is none necessarily preserved but if the
仿射变换没有要求保持不变的量
determinate of the transformation matrix is equal to one.
不过如果变换矩阵的行列式等于1
Then it's not hard to show that the area of this object, so the area inside the
这时不难证明 这个物体的面积
curve or the object itself is preserved and those I call equi-affine motions,
即曲线包含的这个物体的面积是不变的 这样的变换称为等仿射运动
equi-affine transformations, and we're going to often just call them a affine
或等仿射变换 通常简称为仿射
and we're going to assume that we are talking about those that we get with the
假设我们讲的这些变换行列式都等于1
determinant equal to one. Now these are the type of linear
它们都属于线性变换
transformations. We're not going to discuss non-linear.
我们不讨论非线性变换
I can take X and square log Y, things like that we're not going to discuss.
X或logY平方等等 我们都不会讨论到
We're only discussing about multiplying by a matrix, so that means a linear
我们只会讨论乘以一个矩阵的情况 所以只会是线性变换
transformation. So we have Euclidean and we have affine,
现在我们了解了欧几里得和仿射变换
normally equi-affine. So now that we know that we can rotate,
一般是等仿射变换 于是我们可以对曲线 即形状
stretch and do things like that, curves, meaning to shapes.
进行旋转伸缩之类的变换
Let's go back to, for a second, to curvature.
我们暂时回到曲率
We talk about these two guys. The arc length and the curvature.
在那里提到了这两个量 弧长和曲率
The arc length is the parametrization that gives us constant unit length
弧长这个参数代表恒定的单位长度切线
tangents. The curvature is the magnitude of the
曲率是对弧长
second derivative according to the arc length.
求二次导数得到的量值
So if we go around the curve, around this shape, we have, for every point a given
如果我们历遍整条曲线 即整个形状 每个点都能得到一个曲率值
curvature and I'm drawing it here. So S as the parametrization goes around
我把它画到这里 S是这个形状每一点的参量
the shape and for every S I have a point in the curve and then I have a curvature.
每个S对应着曲线上一个点 也对应着一个曲率
Now let's assume I do an Euclidean transformation.
现在假设我做了一个欧几里得变换
I rotate and translate my shape. Something very interesting happens.
对这个形状进行旋转和平移  有趣的事情发生了
There are of course, corresponding points, this point got rotated and
当然 这里有对应的点 这个点旋转和平移到这个点
translated to this one and here is the beauty.
这就是它的美丽所在
There we have the same curvature, so the curvature here.
两个点有相同的曲率 于是这里的曲率
And the curvature here, it's going to be exactly the same value.
和这里的曲率的值是一样的
So, if you were to take the first derivative, second derivative, measured
因此 在两个对应点处的一阶导数
the magnitudes in both corresponding points, exactly the same value.
二阶导数的幅值是相同的
That happens for all the corresponding points.
所有相应的点都会这样
So here we have another pair of corresponding points.
这里我们有另一对对应点
We have the same curvature. Sometimes the curvature will be zero,
他们有相同的曲率 有时曲率会是0
sometimes will be negative. Every pair of corresponding points has
有时会是负数 每对对应点
exactly the same curvature. Every single point.
都有相同的曲率 每个点都是
So basically if we have two shapes, that are related by a rotation and translation
如果我们有两个形状 它们可以互相通过旋转和平移
meaning an Euclidean motion, then their curvatures are identical.
即欧几里得运动联系起来 那么它们的曲率是一致的
Of course, you have to have a starting point, that is, the corresponding where
当然 你必须知道起始点 就是对应的S为0的点
is S equal zero. Once you have that, exactly the same
一旦有了起始点 就能得到两条相同的曲率曲线
curvature. So the curvature uniquely identifies the
因此 曲率可以唯一决定形状
shape, actual rotation and a translation, and that's beautiful. That's a theorem
而形状由平移和旋转决定 这是个美妙的定理
that basically this curve uniquely identifies the curve a meaning the shape
基本上说 这条曲线与这一条曲线相同
inside a curve up to a rotation and a translation.
曲线里面的形状取决于旋转和平移
It actually has been shown these are beautiful results in transformational
已经证明 所有对象都不会因为旋转或平移而发生改变
geometry that every other thing that doesn't change with rotations and
任何的微分都是s和Kappa
translations. Every other differential thing is a
即弧长和曲率的函数
function of S and kappa, of arc length and curvature.
这些在微分几何中是很赞的结论
For example we could take the curvature and the derivative of the curvature, and
例如 我们可以取曲率和曲率的导数
that gives us another crazy curve on the plane.
然后在坐标系上得到另一条变态的曲线
So for every curvature we, we look at, what's the derivative, how much is the
对每个我们要研究的曲率 它们的导数是多少
curvature changing in that point? We do that for one shape.
每一点上的曲率变化了多少？ 下面对一个形状进行运算
We do a rotation and translation. Voila.
作个旋转和平移 Voila(瞧)
We get exactly the same value. And that's theorem in part, basically due
我们得到完全相同的值 这个理论的一部分依据嘉当定理
to Cartan, and they're extensions of the theorem, some even more modern than these
是嘉当定理的扩展 有些甚至比它还前卫
one's but it's the beauty of that, if you have the arc of S and the curvature
但这正是它的美妙之处 现在有了弧长S和曲率Kappa
Kappa, you have all what are called the differential invariance, functions that
于是得到所谓的微分不变性
don't change when you basically do rotations and translations. So basically
只作旋转和平移 函数不会改变
they uniquely identify objects. That up to rotation and translation.
因此它们唯一确定了物体 只取决于旋转或平移
You cannot recover the rotation. They're invariant to them.
你无法恢复旋转  因为它们具有不变性
But basically they uniquely identify those objects up to rotation and
但这些函数只能唯一确定欧式几何中的旋转和平移
translation in Euclidean geometry. Now what happens with affine
那仿射变换又会有怎样的情况呢？
transformations? What happens when we don't just do
如果我们不只是旋转和平移
rotations and translation, but we also allow basically the curve, the shape to
还同时让曲线 形状
stretch and with different stretches in different directions?
在不同方向上进行伸缩  情况会怎样？
Now unfortunately, or fortunately if you like math, not everything in the world of
很不幸 或者说很幸运 如果你喜欢数学
image processing is rotations and translation.
不是所有的图像处理都只有旋转和平移
So let's assume I have a shape like my hand.
下面假设有个像我的手那样的形状
If I only do things like this parallel to the camera.
如果我只像这样 与摄像头平行
I can model the motion of the object by a rotation.
我可以用旋转来作为物体运动的模型
The moment I tilt it towards the camera, and then I do the projection of that on
当我把手向摄像头倾斜 然后向摄像头作个投影
the camera, then this is not any longer just a rotation and a translation.
这时就不仅仅是旋转和平移了
And one of the ways to model this is with these fine transforms.
一个对此可行的建模方法就是仿射变换
So. Basically, if your object is relatively.
如果物体在平面上
On a plane relatively to the distance to the camera.
与到摄像头的距离是相对的
Like here, for example, a drawing on a plane and we are looking, this is the
像这里 我们看到的平面上的一幅画
camera. Us, is the camera.
这是摄像头 把我们想成摄像头
We are looking at kind of a plainer shape then there is affine transform.
我们看到一个很平坦的形状 这里是一个仿射变换
So it is a more general multiplication by a matrix once again because I'm not doing
同样 这是乘以一个矩阵的更一般形式
the rotation and the translations just in, in pilot place to the camera I'm
因为我不止在与摄像头平行的位置作旋转和平移
doing them a bit tilted. And that can be model by an affine
而且还有一点倾斜 这可以用仿射变换来建模
transform, a more general linear transform.
仿射变换是更通用的线性变换
So, we need to extend these basic concepts to basically allow for those
所以我们要扩展这些基本概念
affine transforms. remember an affine transform is a more
来考虑仿射变换 记住仿射变换是
generic, basically matrix.
更具有一般性质的矩阵
We have the x and y, but we multiply by a more general matrix that normally has
这里有x和y 用一个更一般性的矩阵乘以它
unit determinant. We want to preserve areas just to make
这个矩阵行列式一般为1 以保持面积不变
our life easier. We don't need this.
这样可以更方便计算 我们不需要很复杂
We can do all this without, basically a unit determinant, but it's much easier if
我们大可不需要单位行列式 但设定了它会让我们更方便
we assume this. So, when we were talking about rotations
所以 当我们讲到旋转和平移的时候
and translations, remember, we assumed that this column and this column were
记得 我们设定这一列和这一列
orthogonal. So,
是正交的 因此
basically, they're in a product equal to zero,
它们的内积等于0
and they were also normalized to one. And those are rotations and then we have
而且它们是归一化的 这是旋转 这表示平移
a translation. When we assume more generic things like
当我们假设更一般性的矩阵
here, just a unit determinant, those are affine transformed.
像这样单位行列式的 这是仿射变换
And we have kind of this tilting that basically gives us stretchings in the
这里还有点倾斜 有不同角度的伸缩
different directions. So I want to define this arc length and
所以同样地 我们定义仿射变换的弧长和曲率
curvature for the fine case, as well. Now in order to do that, let me just talk
为了做到这些 我讲讲
a bit more of what is parameterization. So I can have a curve parameterized by p
什么是参数化 我可以像往常那样得到一个以p为参数的曲线
as before and can have it marameterized by r by a different parameter.
也可以用另一个参量r来参数化
The curve will basically be the same. By R or by P the parameterization is kind
以r或者以p为参数 得出来的曲线是一样的
of telling me how fast are we traveling the curve.
都表示沿着这条曲线行走的速度
Remember if you take the derivative of the curve according to p you get the
如果对这条曲线以p求导
tangent vector with a certain magnitude. If you take the derivative according to R
你会得到有确定大小的正切向量 如果你求对r求导
you get the same tangent vector same direction with a different magnitude.
你会得到相同方向上大小不同的切向向量
If you remember from basic physics derivatives are velocity.
如果你还记得基础物理 就知道导数其实是速度
So you're only telling me how fast are you traveling the curve.
这就相当于告诉了我走过这条曲线有多快
But you're going from the same point to the same point.
但你的起止点都是相同的
So it's like you are driving the highway between two points.
就像你在高速公路的两点间行驶
And the speed that you drive is the parametrization.
行驶的速度就是参数
But the highway is the curve. The highway doesn't change.
高速公路就是曲线 路是不变的
So when we take functions geometric functions basically of our sorry I want
当我们用几何函数 抱歉
one more let me come back. When we take geometric functions of
回到刚才的幻灯片 当我们取曲线的几何函数
curve, they have to be invariant to parameterizations.
对于每个参量都是不变的
The distance between two points in the highway does not depend on the velocity I
公路上两点的距离不会取决于我驾驶的速度
travel on that highway. So the geometric measurements that we
所以我们的几何测量
take have to be invariant to the parameterization, and they also have to
对于取不同参量 值也是不变的
be invariant to basically the transformations that we want to do,
它需要保持不变 不管我们是作旋转变换
either rotations or affine transformation.
还是仿射变换
So if you take a map and you rotate the map, the distance between two cities has
所以如果你拿一张地图 然后旋转它 两个城市间的距离也是不变的
to remain the same distance, not just because I'm looking at the map
不会因为我用不同方式看地图 城市间的距离就发生变化
differently, it changes. It has to be invariant to that.
距离是不会变的
So let's use this concept to define the arc length S that we saw before.
那么 我们就用这个概念来定义之前讲到的弧长S
Let's just explicitly define it now and we are going to do the same for the
现在明确地定义它 之后我们也将在仿射变换中做相同的定义
affine case. But let's start with Euclidean, so
我们先从欧几里得变换开始
basically, only allowing four rotations. So here is what we have, and this diagram
一般来说 它只允许旋转 我们来看一下 这张图很有意思
is very good. Assume that you have a curve going
假设有条曲线经过这里
through here. And you're going to take a very
我们取一个无穷小量
infinitesimal, very small portion of that curve.
即取曲线的极小一部分
So I have, I can draw a coordinate system, like here and have a, very small
然后我可以画一个坐标系 就像这样
movement in the X direction, and a very small movement in the Y direction.
然后在X方向 和Y方向均有一个微小的移动
And then because of Pythagoras, this is basically X direction is perpendicular to
根据勾股定理 因为X方向垂直于Y方向
the Y direction. So we have that this distance is the
所以我们得到这个距离为
square root of the X direction distance and the Y direction distance, each one of
根号下 X方向上距离的平方 加Y方向上距离的平方
them square. Simple Pythagoras.
简单的勾股定理
So now I'm allowing to multiply and divide by DP.
现在同时乘以除以一个dp
P is my general parametrization. So I multiply and divide by a small
P是一般化的参数 我们乘以除以一个p的微小改变量
change in P. Remember we're basically talking about
记住 我们只是讨论
the curve going around here. So I'm going to just draw that, I have a
这里的曲线 现在我将画出一条曲线
curve and I move a tiny bit X, a tiny bit Y and I measure how much I have moved
在X方向上移动一丁点 在Y方向上移动一小点 然后计算总体移动了多少
there. So I multiply and divide and this curve
对这个式子同时乘以除以dp 而这个曲线为C(p)
is CP. So I multiply and divide by DP, just a
同时乘以除以dp
small variation in the parameterization. And that's basically quality.
dp表示了参数的一个小变化 整个式子还是相等的
And now, I basically move this DP in, so I get DP squared.
现在将这个dp移进根号中 得到dp的平方
Okay? I move it in,
明白？ 将它移进根号中去
but I move it inside a square root, so I have to square it before, so I get this,
因为移入的是一个平方根 所以得先把它平方起来 于是我们得到了这个式子
okay? This is DP stays and this is exactly the
dp在这里 而这正是欧几里得距离的定义
definition of the Euclidean distance, the local, basically distance of the vector,
即距离向量的大小
just basically the definition of that. So we got that DS is simply DP.
我们得到 ds=|Cp| x dp
If we want to get the arc length S, it's basically the integral of that.
如果要得到弧长S 就做它的积分
Okay? So this is the way to go basically from.
明白吗？ 这就是将一般化的参数P转换到
A generic parameterization P to the particular one S in such a way that the
到具体参数S的方法 在这个方法中
derivative now basically is unit length. Always the derivative will be unit
导数就是单位长度的 它总会是单位长度向量
length. It will be a unit length vector.
它是一个单位长度向量
And then the general distance of a curve, the total distance, distance of a curve
接着 曲线的长度 曲线的总长
is the integral of everything from P equals zero to P equal one of CPDP, this
等于 |Cp|dp 从P为0到1的积分
is the definition of the length. And if you basically replace what we have
这是长度的定义 如果你把积分替换为
here is the integral of DS from zero to the length so when your parmitrizing by s
ds从0到长度L的积分 那么 当你以s作为参数时
your not going from zero to one your going from zero to the length.
将不是从0积到1 而是从0积到曲线的长度
Basically once again. This tells us how to go from every
再提一下 这告诉我们
parameterization to A, so from every speed of traveling between two cities, if
如何从一般化的参数得到S 所以从两个城市间的旅行速度来看
you're basically integrating the magnitude of that speed.
如果你对旅途中的速度进行积分
Along the way you're getting kind of a unit length of traveling.
通过这种方法 你会发现旅行的长度是一样的
And that's what then lead us to basically.
待会我们求二阶导数时
The Euclidean curvature when we took basically second derivative.
这个性质会引出欧几里得曲率
So this is for Euclidean. Now Euclidean rotations and translations
所以这就是欧几里得变换时的参数变换 欧几里得旋转和变换
preserve length, and that's why I could use length here.
能保持曲线长度不变 这就是为什么在这里可以使用长度
Now, in the affine case or in particular in the equi-affine case,
现在 在仿射的情形中 或者是更特别的等仿射情形中
length is not preserve anymore. What's preserved?
长度不再保持不变 那什么保持不变呢？
Area. So I can take areas.
面积会保持不变 所以我可以考虑求面积
Now, in order to take areas, I need two vectors.
为了求得面积 我需要两个向量
One vector does not define an area, I need two.
一个向量不能求出面积 两个才行
So, I'm basically going to take the first derivative.
所以 我要求出一阶导数
It's always a tangent V is going to be now my affine arclength.
它还是表示了切线 而V就是仿射变换的弧长
So the first derivative is not the unit vector.
所以一阶导数就不会是单位长度的了
That's a characteristic only when you take derivatives according to S, to the
那个性质 只有当你对S 对欧几里得弧长求导时才成立
Euclidean arc length. So I take a first derivative, and a
所以我求得一阶导数 和二阶导数
second. Again, these two vectors not
再说一遍 这两个向量一般是不会垂直的
perpendicular in general. That's a property only when you take
这个性质 只有当你对弧长S求导时才成立
derivatives according to arc length. And then I basically define the, I look
然后我着眼于面积
at the area and I'm going to look for the parameterization V that when I take first
寻找参数V 使得在求一阶导数和
derivative. Second derivative this area is equal to
和二阶导数时 这个区域的面积等于1
one. I define it that way and basically you
我通过这种方式定义参数V 你可以自己做一些数学推算
can do all the math. We take, the first derivative is a
我们求出一阶导数 它是一个向量
vector, and the second derivative is a vector,
二阶导数也是一个向量
and we put them here as vectors in a 2 by 2 matrix.
然后我们将它们作为向量构成一个 2x2 的矩阵
So remember, this is a vector, this is a vector, so we get the 2 by 2 matrix.
所以请记住 这两个都是向量 所以我们得到一个 2x2 的矩阵
It's of this form. It's basically.
它基本上就是这种形式
Let me write it down explicitly. X, derivative B, Y, derivative B, XVV,
我来把它写来下 Xv Yv Xvv Yvv
YVV. And that creates a matrix.
它们构成了一个矩阵
And I'm going to ask for the determinate of this matrix the determinate of a
然后我要来求这个矩阵的行列式
matrix is the area of the parallelogram defined by these two vectors and now I'm
一个矩阵的行列式等于 由这两个向量组成的平行四边形的面积
giving you a new concept at, at. A, group of concepts that you might not
现在我讲了一个新的概念 一堆你可能不熟悉的概念
be familiar with. But I am defining them on the way.
但是我从头开始定义了它们
So they, if I have a two x two matrix, this is a vector, this is a vector.
如果我有一个 2x2 的矩阵 这是一个向量 这也是一个向量
The determinant of these is the area of the parallelogram between these two
它的行列式就等于 这两个向量组成的平行四边形的面积
vectors, exactly what we have here. And I'm going to ask that to be equal to
就如这里所示 然后让其等于1
one. And remember for euclidean we ask the
记住 对于欧几里得变换 我们要求长度等于1
length to be equal to one here we ask for the area to be equal to one.
而这里 我们要求面积等于1
I don't want to proof too many things to you but any parameterization p will give
我不想向你证明太多东西 但是任何参数p
a new parameterization that holds this property following this integral.
都能推算出一个新的参数v 它能通过这个积分计算得到
Okay? So that's a theorem.
明白了吗？ 这是个定理
Just believe it for now. Now in particular, I can take p equal to
现在相信它是正确的就可以了 特别地 我可以令p等于欧几里得弧长
the Euclidean arc length. That's allowed to do.
这样的设定是可以的
So I can put cs and css. Now what are these two guys?
所以这里变成了Cs和Css 那这两个是什么呢？
This is unit length. Okay, unit length,
这是一阶导数 而且是单位长度的
and the second derivative in the case of the Euclidean arc length, is
在欧几里得弧长的例子中 二阶导数垂直于
perpendicular to the first one, and it has basically length equal to curvature,
一阶导数 并且它的大小等于曲率
Euclidean. So this is one, this is curvature.
所以这等于1 这等于曲率
So, of course, this area is equal to curvature.
所以面积的大小等于曲率
So we get that V, the, a fine arc length, gets its.
我们得到了仿射弧长V
Obtain by the integral of the kregen curvature to the one third.
可以由k的三分之一次方的积分得到
The S. And therefore what we get is an extremely
通过这个积分式子 我们得到了欧几里得弧长和
interesting relationship between the Euclidean arc length and defined arc
仿射弧长之间一个非常有意思的关系
length. So we have the Euclidean arc length
所以我们可以从仿射弧长得到欧几里得弧长
coming from here and defined arc length and they're related by the Euclidean
它们通过欧几里得曲率联系起来
curvature. This is a beautiful relationship in
这是微分几何中一个美妙的关系式
differential geometry that relates Euclidean differential geometry with
它联系了欧几里得微分几何和仿射微分几何
defined differential geometry. Now we have defined arc length, our next
现在 我们有了仿射弧长这个概念
step is to find defined curvature. How do we do that in a very similar
下一步是求出仿射曲率 那如何才能求出仿射曲率呢？
fashion as we did for the kleeant case if you remember in the kleeant case we
这里用到的方法和之前求K的方法非常相似 如果你还记得在欧几里得变换中求K的方法
started by basically doing the derivative.
我们先从求导开始
Of the property. That this was equal to one we say the
利用它的性质 这个式子等于1
length is constant and we took derivatives now we have to the area is
在长度不变的情况下 我们求了导数 而现在是面积不变
constant when we use the fine arc length so here remember is a determinant of two
面积的定义用到了仿射弧长 记住 这是两个向量构成的矩阵的行列式
vectors. And we're going to take the derivative.
然后我们对其求导
The derivative of the determinant is like any other product.
求行列式的导数和求其他乘积导数的规则一样
We have to take the derivative of the first vector and then put the second and
我们必须求出第一个向量的导数 第二个向量保持不变
then the derivative of the second and put the first.
接着求出第二个向量的导数 第一个向量保持不变
So it's what we have here. The derivative of the determinant of
于是得到这里的式子 Cv Cvv两个向量组成的行列式的导数
these two vectors, cv and c, vv, is the determinant here, derivative of the first
它等于是这里的行列式 第一个向量的导数
and we keep the second plus the derivative of the second and we keep the
第二个向量不变 再加上这个行列式 第二个向量的导数 第一个向量不变
first. Now if we have a determinate with two
如果一个行列式的两个列是相同的
identical columns that's zero so this basically is zero that's a very basic
那么它就等于0 所以这个为0 这是线性代数中很基础的知识
property of linear algebra. So we end up that the determinant here.
这样一来 这里的行列式
Is equal to zero which means once again that these two vectors are parallel.
它的值等于0  这就说明了这两个向量是平行的
When we took derivatives here, we basically had that.
当我们对这个式子求导数时 得到这么一个结论
In their product to be zero, the two vectors have to be perpendicular.
当两个向量的内积等于0时 这两个向量一定是相互垂直的
For the determinant to be zero, the two vectors have to be parallel.
当两个向量的行列式等于0时 这两个向量一定是平行的
Another basic property again of linear algebra.
这也是线性代数中的基础知识
So the first and the third derivative, when I'm taking derivatives according to
所以当对仿射弧长求导时 它的一阶导数和二阶导数是两个向量
defined arc length, these two vectors are parallel.
而这两个向量是平行的
So they are basically parallel. One for example goes in this direction.
它们是平行的 比如说 其中一个向量沿这个方向
The other goes in this direction. The ratio between them.
另一个沿着这个方向 我们将它们的比值
We define as defined curvature, the same way that we use the magnitude.
定义为仿射曲率 这种定义方式和之前
of the second derivative, according to Euclidean arc length, we use this as
定义欧几里得曲率的方式相同 它用到了欧几里得弧长二阶导数的大小
Euclidean curvature, the ratio between these two parallel vectors is affine
而这两个平行向量的比值就是仿射曲率
curvature. And it's not hard to show that this new,
不难看出 这个新定义的曲率u
this affine curvature is an affine variant.
这个仿射曲率是仿射不变的
What I mean is very simple if we take as we talk before, an affine transformation
我想要表达的意思很简单 如果做一个之前讨论的变换
preserving area remember equi-affine. So we have a curve the boundary of a
仿射变换会保持面积不变 记住 这里是等仿射变换 我们有一个曲线
shape and we're taking a fine transformation.
一个物体边界的曲线 然后 我们做一个仿射变换
We compute the fine curvature of this shape as a function of the affine arc
计算这个曲线的仿射曲率 它是曲线的仿射弧长的一个函数
length of the shape. we do the same for the new curve.
对于变换后的曲线 我们也计算出它的仿射曲率
And voila, they're identical. So in the same way as we have Euclidean
瞧 它们完全相同 所以 这和欧几里得变换一样
properties, with S and Kappa, Euclidean arc length and Euclidean curvature, we
根据欧几里得变换 S和K 欧几里得弧长和欧几里得曲率 它们的关系不会改变
have them with the affine arc length and affine curvature.
仿射弧长和仿射曲率之间的关系也不会改变
They're basically the same, and they completely identify the object,
它们基本是相同的 在仿射变换中
up to on a fine transform. So now you're an expert on planar
它们能完全标识出一个对象 现在 你对平面微分几何已经很了解了
differential geometry. You know the concept of arc length.
你知道了弧长的概念
It is particular parametrization that gives us some interesting property about
它是一个特别的参数 它给出了曲线的一些有趣的性质
the curve, like constant speed in the Euclidean case.
比如 欧几里得变换中恒定大小的一阶导数
or constant area in the affine case, and then from that, we got the curvature that
或者 仿射变换中恒定大小的面积 从这些性质中 我们得到了曲率
is identical. For the Euclidean case, after rotations.
在欧几里得变换中 在旋转之后 欧几里得曲率是不变的
For the affine case, after affine transforms.
在仿射变换中 仿射变换之后 仿射曲率是不变的
So those are very simple functions that uniquely identify shapes because they
所以曲率是关于弧长很简单的函数 它们能唯一确定出一个形状
uniquely identify curves. Now our next step is basically, let's
唯一确定出一条曲线 接下来 我们要做的是
extend that a tiny bit to basically surfaces.
将这些概念向曲面做一些扩展
And we're going to do that in the next video,
我们将在下一个视频中学习这些知识
and then you're going to have the basic tools of differential geometry to go and
那时 你能把微分几何学的知识作为基本工具
do the formations of curves and to do image processing and understand active
处理曲线的形态以及做一些有关的图像处理 并且能够理解主动轮廓的知识
contours. So I see you in the next video for that.
那么 让我们在下一个视频中再见吧
Thank you.
谢谢大家